Guide to the Café Nicholson Archive MSS.165
Fales Library and Special Collections
Café Nicholson Archive
1948-2005
Fales Library and Special Collections
Nicholson, John, 1916-2016
MSS.165
2 Linear Feet in 1 record carton, 1 manuscript box, and 1 oversize flat box
Café Nicholson was opened in 1949 by Johnny Nicholson and closed over 50 years later in 2000. The restaurant was famous for its exploration of food innovation prior to this trend becoming popular. The luxurious interior decor of the restaurant in combination with its unique menu made Café Nicholson a hotspot for celebrities and other individuals in the upper echechelons of New York City society. This collection of photographs, newspaper and magazine clippings, publications, and Café Nicholson memorabilia all give a distinct sense of the character and culture of the restaurant and its significance to New York City social, cultural and culinary history. Materials in this collection date from 1948 to 2005.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by John Nicholson, 1984. The accession number associated with this gift is 2005.165
Arrangement
The records are arranged into four series with an additional series for oversize materials listed at the end. Series I contains five subseries which are arranged chronologically. Series II, III, and IV are arranged alphabetically. The series and subseries arrangement of the records is as follows:
Series I: Scrapbooks
Subseries A: Scrapbook I
Subseries B: Scrapbook II
Subseries C: Scrapbook III
Subseries D: Scrapbook IV
Subseries E: Scrapbook V
Series II: Correspondence
Series III: Printed Materials
Subseries A: Articles, Reviews, Mentions
Subseries B: Books
Series IV: Objects and Memorabilia
Oversize Series I: Scrapbooks
Historical Note
Café Nicholson was opened in 1949 by Johnny Nicholson. Born to Albanian immigrants, Nicholson moved from St Louis to New York after he was declared exempt from military service. Nicholson originally had dreams of becoming a fashion designer, but after an unsuccessful stint in the design industry, Nicholson opened a modest cafe on Manhattan's Upper East Side. Nicholson's good friend and extraordinary southern cook, Edna Lewis co-owned the restaurant until the mid 1970s and made Café Nicholson famous for its fabulous cuisine--especially its chocolate souffle. Café Nicholson was a pioneering establishment in the restaurant industry because it was invested in food innovation long before food innovation was popular. Over the years Café Nicholson moved around to several addresses on Manhattan's Upper East Side, although it is most remembered for its location near the Queensborough Bridge. After nearly fifty successful and memorable years, Café Nicholson closed its doors in 2000.
Known for its lavish greco-roman interior, inspired by Café Greco in Rome, Café Nicholson made the ideal background for fashion magazine photo shoots, and various advertisements. Filmmaker Woody Allen used the restaurant for a scene in his 1994 movie, Bullets Over Broadway. Soon after its opening in 1949, the combination of its decor, consistently good food, and lively personal staff, established Café Nicholson as one of New York's fashionable hotspots. In addition to members of high society, Café Nicholson attracted artistic and literary figures such as Tennessee Williams, Gore Vidal, Jean Renoir and many more. Photographer Karl Bissinger documented this scene and many of his original photographs are included in the collection. Café Nicholson's client list included a range of celebrities, movie stars, politicians, old New York aristocrats and young "up and comings". In the center of this glamorous, theater-like setting was Johnny Nicholson energically running the show with his parrot Lolita perched on his shoulder. Tiffany and Co.'s design director John Loring commented, "High society loves to meet high bohemia, and at Johnny's that made for a certain cafe society." Café Nicholson holds a unique place in New York City social memory.
Related Material at Fales Library and Special Collections
Cecily Brownstone Papers (MSS.134)
Les Dames d'Escoffier New York Archive (MSS.150)
Scope and Contents
The collection, consisting of photographs, newspaper and magazine clippings, publications, and Café Nicholson memorabilia, gives a distinct sense of the character and culture of the restaurant and its significance to post WWII New York City social, cultural, and culinary history. Materials in this collection date from 1948 to 2005.
The collection is organized into four series with an additional series for oversize material.
Series I is composed of materials from 5 scrapbooks compiled by Johnny Nicholson. Arranged in rough chronological order, the scrapbooks document the restaurant from the early 1950s through to the restaurant closing in 2000. Series I contains clippings from newspapers and magazines as well as visual materials including small paintings and Karl Bissinger photographs of restaurant patrons including Paul Bowles, Hoagy Carmichael, Jenny Tourel, Jean Renoir and others.
Series II consists of correspondence to Johnny Nicholson from various restaurant patrons.
Series III contains printed materials and is organized into two subseries, one for articles, mentions, and reviews of the restaurant; the second for books with mentions of the restaurant.
Series IV consists of Café Nicholson objects and memorabilia.
Restaurants -- New York (State) -- New York; Dinners and dining -- New York.; Gastronomy.; Women cooks -- United States.; Cooks -- United States; Nicholson, John, 1916-2016; Bissinger, Karl; Lewis, Edna; Cafe Nicholson
- Series I: Scrapbooks
  Scope and Contents note
  Series I is composed of materials from 5 scrapbooks compiled by Johnny Nicholson. Arranged in rough chronological order, the scrapbooks document the restaurant from the early 1950s through to the restaurant closing in 2000. Series I contains clippings from newspapers and magazines as well as visual materials including small paintings and Karl Bissinger photographs of restaurant patrons including Paul Bowles, Hoagy Carmichael, Jenny Tourel, Jean Renoir and others.
  - Subseries A: Scrapbook I
    This subseries consists of materials from Scrapbook I, dating from June 1948-July 1952 when Café Nicholson was located at 212 East 58th Street, New York, NY.
    - Typescript, "Mr. Nicholson's Magical, Moveable Feast." By Michael Batterbury, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Two photocopies of black and photographs, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - One 8"x10" black and white photograph by Gerry Mandell, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Two 8"x10" black and white photographs by Gerry Mandell, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - One 9"x11.5" watercolor by Richard De Menocal, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - One 10"x7", one 8"x11" and three 4"x5" black and white photographs of Jenny Tourel by Karl Bissinger, ca. 1950 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Printed materials of fashion photographs from unknown magazines, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Photocopy of 8"x10" black and white photograph taken by Karl Bissenger of Tanaquil Le Clercq, Donald Windham, Buffie Johnson, Tennessee Williams, Gore Vidal and Edna Lewis., undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - One 8"x11" black and white photograph of Charles Russell Bennett by Karl Bissinger, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - One 9"x 11.5" black and white photograph of Hoagy Carmichael by Karl Bissinger, ca. 1950 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - One 7.5"x 8.5" black and white photograph of Gower and Marge Champion by Karl Bissinger, ca. 1950 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Magazine clipping of Karl Bissinger photograph of Jean Renoir, ca. 1950 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Mixed media painting by Tom Prentiss, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - NY Herald Tribune clipping, "New Discovery in Restaurants", by Clementine Paddleford, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Subseries B:Scrapbook II
    This subseries consists of materials from Scrapbook II, dating from 1952-1954, when Café Nicholson was at 323 East 58th Street and Café New Johnny was at 146 East 57th Street
    - Clipping from Town and Country, "New Years' Newest", 1953 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Clippings from unknown publications including review by Herb Caan, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Clipping from unknown publication, "New Johnny's Café a Decorator's Dream," by Clementine Paddleford, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Subseries C: Scrapbook III
    This subseries consists of materials from Scrapbook III, dating from 1954-1967, when Café Nicholson was at 147 East 57th Street
    - Cover of The Continental Magazine, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Full page layout in unknown publication, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - One 9"x11.5" black and white photograph of restaurant facade, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - New York Times clipping, "Restaurant on Review," by Craig Claiborne, ca. 1964 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Clippings from unknown publications, undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Town and Country and DeCor Furs advertisement, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Clippings from unknown publications including Saks Fifth Ave advertisement, undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - One 8"x10" black and white photograph of Paul Bowles by Karl Bissinger for Millicent Dillon's "A Little Original Sin", undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Advertisement from unknown publication, undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Two 8"x10" black and white photographs, photographer unknown., undated (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Old Charter Bourbon advertisement, undated (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Two "with compliments" cards, and one copy of photograph from unknown publication, undated (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Subseries D: Scrapbook IV
    This subseries consists of materials from Scrapbook IV, dating from 1967-1999, when Café Nicholson was at 320 East 57th Street
    - Fourteen page feature article in Mademoiselle magazine, photographs by David McCabe, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - One 4"x6" color photograph, printed invitation, and 4"x6' mounted print of a pastel drawing by Jared Barn, ca. 1988 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Three 4"x6" color photographs, and two 3.5"x4.5" color photographs, 1981, undated (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Photocopy from New York Cookbook, by Molly O'Neil, undated (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Misc. printed materials and copy of color photograph from closing night at Café Nicholson, 1967, 1995 and undated (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Subseries E: Scrapbook V
    This subseries consists of materials from Scrapbook V, dating from 1967-1999, when Café Nicholson was at 323 East 58th Street
    - Four 8"x10" color photographs of the restaurant interior, undated (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Two 8"x10" color stills taken from the Woody Allen film "Bullets Over Broadway", undated (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - Two 8"x10" black and white photographs of the restaurant interior, undated (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - Clipping from On the Town in New York City by Michael and Araine Batterberry, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 53)
    - Misc. printed materials from Forbes Magazine, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 54)
    - Printed materials, unknown publication, photograph of Edna Lewis, undated (Box 1, Folder 58)
    - Printed materials, unknown publication, Benson and Hedges 100s advertisement, undated (Box 1, Folder 60)
    - Seven 8"x10" black and white photographs by Bill Cummingham, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 63)
    - Misc. enclosures and color copy of "staff" photograph, 1952-71 (Box 1, Folder 66)
    - Misc. enclosures, Forbes correspondence, 1994, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 67)
    - Misc. enclosures from the end of scrapbook (Box 1, Folder 68)
- Series II: Correspondence
  Correspondence to Johnny Nicholson. The bulk of the materials date from the 1980s-1990s; some items are undated.
  - Correspondence A-D, various (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Correspondence E-H, various (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Correspondence I-L, various (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - Correspondence M-P, various (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - Correspondence Q-T, various (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - Correspondence U-Z, various (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - Correspondence, misc envelopes, various (Box 1, Folder 75)
- Series III: Printed Materials
  Articles, reviews, mentions and books
  - Subseries A: Articles, Reviews, Mentions
    - Article from Architectural Digest, "Brendan Gill: Café Nicholson", 1992 (Box 2, Folder 76)
    - Article from Diversion, "Café Nicholson" by Geri Trotta, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 77)
    - Article from Esquire magazine, "A Café That's Never Open" by Suzanne O'Malley, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 78)
    - Mention in Gourmet magazine, "Specialities de la Maison" by Donald Aspinwall Allan, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 79)
    - Advertisement from The New Yorker, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 80)
    - Mention from The New Yorker, "Talk of the Town", 1975 (Box 2, Folder 81)
    - Mention from New York Magazine, "The Place to Be" by John Homans and Marc Jacobson, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 82)
    - New Yorkskiye Sezony, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 83)
    - Advertisement in The Playbill, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 84)
    - Advertisement in The Playbill, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 85)
    - Advertisement in The Playbill, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 86)
    - Advertisement in The Playbill, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 87)
    - Prestige Art, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 88)
    - Mention in New York Magazine, "Blow-Out: The Decline and Fall of the Fashion Photographer" by Owen Edwards, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 89)
    - article in Vanity Fair, "High Bohemia" by Gore Vidal, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 90)
    - Article in Vanity Fair, "A Nightspot to Remember" by Mary Cantwell, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 90A)
  - Subseries B: Books
    - ABC-The Museum of Modern Art New York, by Florence Casen Mayers, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 91)
    - The New York Times Guide to Dining Out in New York, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 92)
    - The New York Times Guide to Dining Out in New York, by Brian Miller, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 93)
    - The New York Times Guide to Restaurants in New York City, 1991-1992 (Box 2, Folder 94)
    - On the Town in New York From 1776 to the Present, by Michael and Ariane Batterberry (Box 2, Folder 95)
    - Richtig Reisen New York, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 96)
    - The Tiffany Gourmet Cookbook by John Loring, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 97)
    - Zagat Survey 1999 New York City Restaurants (Box 2, Folder 98)
- Series IV: Objects and Memorabilia
  Restaurant related objects and memorabilia.
  - Staff ledgerbook, 1962-65 (Box 2, Folder 99)
  - Matchbooks, undated (Box 2, Folder 100)
- Oversize Series I: Scrapbooks
  Oversize materials from scrapbooks in Series I.
  - Oversize - Subseries A: Scrapbook I
    - Color copy of a photograph of unknown painting, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Oversize - Subseries C: Scrapbook III
    - Color copy of a photograph, undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Fashion of the Times, Crompton Velvet advertisement, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Clipping from unknown magazine, undated (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - New York Times Magazine, "Swinging Victorians", 1966 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Clipping from unknown publication, "Tabled Tables", undated (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - New York Journal-American, "Shirt Waist Revival", 1959 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Today's Living, "Neon Lights", 1959 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - clipping from unknown publication, "Life of the Party", 1960 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Oversize - Subseries D: Scrapbook IV
    - The Washington Post, "Auditioning New Roles", 1970 (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - The New York Times, "Ambassador" advertisement, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - New York Post, "New York's Romantic Restaurants", 1973 (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - W Magazine, "In and Out", 1987 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Oversize - Subseries E: Scrapbook V
    - New York Times Magazine, "Remembrance of A Souffle Past", 1979 (Box 3, Folder 50)
    - Various clippings, The Wall Street Journal and the New York Times, 1990-91 (Box 3, Folder 51)
    - Clipping from unknown publication, "Center Pieces to Taste With the Eye", undated (Box 3, Folder 55)
    - page from the New York Times Magazine, undated (Box 3, Folder 56)
    - New York Times Magazine, Geoffrey Bean advertisement, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 57)
    - Hanes advertisement, undated (Box 3, Folder 59)
    - Vogue, Trevira advertisement, undated (Box 3, Folder 61)
    - W Magazine, "Louise Eats Out", 1987 (Box 3, Folder 64)
    - New York Times, "The Evening Hours", 1985 (Box 3, Folder 65)